Inventory of the Samuel H. McNutt Papers 1861-1864
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Samuel H. McNutt Papers, 1861-1864.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. Acc. 1997.51
92 items.
Sixty-six letters home from Corporal Samuel H. McNutt of Company H, 12th Pennsylvania Reserves from camps in Maryland and Virginia. Includes comments on battles of Mechanicsville, Gaines Mill, Malvern Hill and Gettysburg.
Samuel H. McNutt.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 92 items, 08/20/1997.
Alternative Form
There are typescripts available for twenty of the sixty-six letters.
Scope and Content Information
Sixty-six letters home from Corporal Samuel H. McNutt of Company H, 12th Pennsylvania Reserves from camps in Maryland and Virginia. Includes comments on battles of Mechanicsville, Gaines Mill, Malvern Hill and Gettysburg.
A history of the 12th Regiment Reserves Infantry can be found in Folder 1 of this collection.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into three series: 1. Introduction, 2. Letters, 3. Typescripts.
Arrangement
Series 2. Letters is arranged by date. Information about the one photograph in this collection can be found between the second and third series.
Samuel McNutt Letter Index
List of letters written home from Samuel McNutt of Company H, 12th Pennsylvania Reserves, at camps Maryland and Virginia.
Hagerstown, Maryland, 26 June 1861 - Camp Negley, Washington County, Maryland.
Camp Curtain - Sunday, Probably July, 1851.
Camp Georgetown Heights - 14 August 1851.
Camp McCall - 19 August 1861.
Washington City, D.C. - 12th Regt Co.H Pennsylvania R.C. Vols. Headquarters Co. McCall, 22 August 1861.
Camp Curtain - 26 August 1861.
Monday, 28 [1861].
Camp Tenally, Headquarters Company - 27 August 1861.
Partial Letter, n.d., probably August 1861.
Camp Tenally, Headquarters - 8 September 1861.
Camp Tenally, Headquarters of the Army of the Potomac - 17 September 1861.
Camp Tenally, U.S.A. Headquarters, 20 September 1861.
Camp Tenally - 28 September 1861.
Camp Tenallytown, Headquarters of the Army of the Potomac Camps - 6 October 1861.
Camp Pierpont, Headquarters of Penn.R.C. - 15 October 1861.
Camp Pierpont - 15 December 1861, poem.
Camp Pierpont - 11 January 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 12 January 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 20 January 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 11 February 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 15 February 1862.
26 February 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 27 February 1862.
Camp Pierpont - 12 March 1862.
Camp Pierpont - Sunday, 15 March 1862.
Camp at Bull Run Bridge - 19 March 1862.
Camp at Bull Run Bridge - n.d.
Camp near Alexandria - 22 March 1862.
Camp near Alexandria -Sabbath Morning, 28 March 1862.
Camp at Manassas Junction - 14 April 1862.
Camp at Capital Hill - 22 April 1862.
Catlett Station - 23 April 1862.
Catlett Station - 28 April 1862.
May 1862.
Camp near Falmouth, Virginia - 20 May 1862.
Camp near Fredericksburg, Virginia - 1 June 1862.
Peninsula Campaign - Tuesday Morning, 17 June 1862.
Camp near Mechanicsville, Virginia - Sabbath, 22 June 1862.
Camp near Supply Point, James River, Battle of Mechanicsville, Gaines Mill, and Malvern Hill - 4 July 1862.
Camp near Harrison's Landing, James River, Battle of Mechanicsville and Gaines Mill - 8 July 1862.
Camp near Harrison's Landing, James River - 17 July 1862.
Camp near Rappahannock Station - 12 August 1862.
Camp near Fredericksburg, Virginia - 21 August 1862.
Camp near Sharpsburg - 15 October 1862.
31 October 1862.
Brooks Station - 4 December 1862.
Camp in the Battlefield of Fredericksburg - 16 December 1862.
Camp near Belle Plain, Virginia - 18 January 1863.
Camp near Belle Plain - 24 January 1863.
Camp near Belle Plain, Virginia - 14 April 1863.
Camp Capital Hill, Washington D.C. - 28 April 1863.
Camp Capital Hill, Washington D.C. - [5 May 1863.]
Camp Upton Hill, Virginia - 3 June 1863.
Upton Hill, Virginia - 18 June 1863.
Camp near Gettysburg, Account of the Battle of Gettysburg - 5 July 1863
Camp near Washington - 2 August 1863.
Camp near Bealton Station, on the railroad - 6 August 1863.
Camp Rappahannock, Concerning the Battle of Gettysburg - 14 August 1863.
Camp Rappahannock, Concerning shooting deserters - Sunday, 30 August 1863.
Camp near Culpeper, Bristoe Campaign - 16 October 1863, also 22 October 1863.
Camp Germania Mills, Virginia - 17 November 1863.
Camp Germania Mills, Virginia - 20 November 1863.
Partial Letter - Probably March 1864.
Camp of Company "H", 12th P.R., Concerning bushwhackers killing troops - 16 April 1863.
Camp on the battle line near Spottsylvania Court House - Friday, 10 o'clock a.m., 20 May.
Letter Fragment - n.d.
Index Terms
Subjects:
United States. Army. Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment, 12th. Company H.; Malvern Hill (Va.), Battle of, 1862.; Gettysburg (Pa.), Battle of, 1863.; Seven Days' Battles, 1862.
Contents List
  Series 1: Introduction
- Introduction, n.d., 5 items. (Folder 1)
  Items includes a signature of Samuel H. McNutt, a copy of McNutt's service record, a list of letters with dates written by Samuel H. McNutt, and a brief history of the 12th Regiment Reserves infantry.
  Series 2: Letters
- Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 26 June 1861 - 16 April 1864, n.d., 66 items. (Folder 2-8)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 26 June 1861 - 8 September 1861., 10 items. (Folder 2)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 17 September 1861 - 11 February 1862., 10 items. (Folder 3)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 15 February 1862 - 14 April 1862., 10 items. (Folder 4)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 22 April 1862 - July 8, 1862., 10 items. (Folder 5)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 17 July 1862 - 14 April 1863., 10 items. (Folder 6)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 28 April 1863 - 16 October 1863., 10 items. (Folder 7)
  - Letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 17 November 1863 - 16 April 1864, n.d., 6 items. (Folder 8)
- Photograph of Samuel H. McNutt, n.d., 1 item. 2.5" x 4.75". Black and white photograph. (Folder 9)
  Series 3: Typescripts
- Typescripts of the letters of Samuel H. McNutt, 26 June 1861 - 16 April 1864., 20 items. (Folder 10)
  The following letters are available as typescripts:
  26 June 1861.
  18 Jan. [1862].
  26 Feb. 1862.
  28 March 1862.
  14 April 1862.
  1 June 1862.
  17 June 1862.
  22 June 1862.
  4 July 1862.
  8 July 1862.
  17 July 1862.
  15 October 1862.
  16 Dec. 1862.
  14 April 1863.
  5 July 1863.
  2 August [1863].
  14 August [1863].
  16 Oct. 1863.
  17 Nov. 1863.
  16 April 1864.